[Music]
hi and welcome to this session about
what's new in designing generative AI
experiences for business Central I'm yo
vinda I'm the design manager for
business Central and I'm here today with
my colleague s alexanderson thank you
yob welcome to this session let's just
Dive Right
In first of all let's set the scene AI
is here to stay and it's bringing more
transformation than most of us have seen
in our
lifetime And in regards to designing
business applications and software
there's a balancing act because all
these great opportunities and Innovation
also means transformation it means
change uh and
disruption but on the human side we
don't like that we like habits we like
predictability and we have expectations
for how features should work and we take
comfort that they work today the same
way as they did
yesterday so that's what this session is
all about how can we make those two ends
meet how can you and we design features
that bring Innovation that make you and
your customers more productive but
without disrupting thing so today we're
going to talk about the design elements
in ux framework for making these
features consistent and seamless and
intuitive and with that yakob can you
tell us a bit more about AI in sort of a
Microsoft context and what we mean when
we say interact with software a new
way I can thanks a lot son um so AI has
been hard to miss in the technology
landscape the last year uh and the
Microsoft take on on AI is using the
name co-pilot to describe the way that
the human and the computer can work
together uh when when AI is in
play and the term copilot is meant to
signify that the computer is not taking
control the computer is working with the
human user to solve the task and that
distinction that way of placing the AI
in relation to what the human does
is key for how we are integrating AI
into business Central as
well so co-pilot is a uh term and it can
be a bit hard in the beginning to really
frame or Define what co-pilot is and
that is partly because it can take many
forms in how users are using a computer
uh with AI going forward so in one way
it's a conversation you've seen the chat
interfaces in other situations it
operates more like you would expect an
AI assistant to do an agent and so on so
we are using this uh story that you
might know from uh Old Times where we
have a group of people who are meeting
an elephant and they are all blindfolded
so they can't see what they are
observing or what they are uh
experiencing but and that for that
reason they describe this new thing that
they don't know in very many different
ways but in reality it's the same
elephant that they're touching so in
this session we will try to get a little
more concrete around what is this
elephant if you will and how are users
going to experience it in business
Central and other Microsoft
software so the agenda for the session
here is um son will explain in a moment
about AI inputs and
outputs uh we will talk about about the
concrete ways where the human and
computer work together so solve the task
and that's framed as a human in the loop
uh way of doing things then we are going
to be more practical we're going to look
at the prompt dialogue in all its
different facets which is an important
uh part of the toolkit in business
Central and lastly we will give you a
lot of uh guidelines and links for where
you can continue your um path into AI
with business Central so over to you s
inputs and outputs for AI let's talk
about the AI inputs and outputs and to
kick this off let's start with a small
demo so here in this example I'm on a
sales order and I want to suggest sales
lines with co-pilot so hit the action
suggest sales lines here I have a free
text input so here here here I can
describe anything I want so let me say I
want uh the uh colia if I Columbia
beans five
pieces and now copile will
generate an interpret my request and
let's see if it could come up with what
I expect it
to so the this part you're see now is
the second mode of the co-pilot The
Prompt
dialogue and now I see that co-pilot
produced an output for me and it's
exactly what I wanted in this case
you'll notice that the output is
structured it's structured into the
fields that I want for example the
quantity field and the item number in
this case that's great this was just to
show you one example where we started
with unstructured data in terms of free
text and ended with structure data in
terms of uh data in controls with field
value so let's talk about this with
inputs so as we saw we had an example
with unstructured input which is free
text and this is also what you know from
various chat experiences you can chat
and and and write anything you like
there's also the structured inputs which
we'll get back to a demo of later where
you have every input in terms of a field
or multiple fields and some settings and
then you have a mix of these two which
is semi-structured you have some free
text but you also have some options that
you can select which helps give input to
the underlying
prompt now if we look at the outputs
it's kind of the same thing you have
outputs that are free text and that's
not necessarily correlated with what
type of inputs it was you can have
structured input and unstructured output
or vice
versa and then you also have the
structured output that we just saw in
the demo before where you have controls
and Fields that are filled with some
values and you can have anything in
between those
two if we take a closer look at the
prompt dialogue it has three stages it
has the input mode it has the generating
mode and it has the output mode and as
we've said a couple of times now input
can be structured semi-structured or
unstructured and the same goes for the
output mode and it's up to you to
consider what fit what fits best for
your scenario for the feature you want
to build do I have structured data do I
have unstructured data because with
unstructured data there's also a bit
more uncertainty as to whether co-pilot
will interpret uh the input correctly
because you could write anything so
consider really if there's an
opportunity to save a few clicks by
using structure data if you have
it now what we see here on screen now is
an example of structured data for the
marketing text feature we have most of
the data here already you have the the
the name of the item you have the item
attributes all all of these things make
up all the input that we need combined
with the options below we can set the
tone and format and emphasis which is
enough for us to feed the prompt so what
happens in in reality is that you can
actually in this case even skip if you
wanted to in some cases skip the input
mode that's up to you to decide for each
of of of your
features now you have control over this
input section um think of it as a place
where you can add page parts and Design
what kind of elements do we want to have
here what is it that the user should be
able to select from uh if not free text
what kind of fields do they want to uh
manipulate in order to feed the prompt
with
input then as we enter the generating
mode this is really where um copilot
does its magic and and and interprets
The Prompt and tries to produce um uh a
meaningful
output then we enter the output mode and
in this example here on screen this is
unstructured data this is this is free
text as the marketing text and on this
screen you have the opportunity to to
manipulate the output in various ways um
again you you take control over this
output space whether or not you want to
show uh like the output as as
unstructured data as here or if you want
to to show it as structured with field
values as we saw in the U demo with the
sales line suggestions as
before you have various options to to do
things on this on this uh page one is to
Carousel between the versions of output
so if if you've iterated through this um
the let's say the generation mode you
have the option to to cycle through the
outputs to select the one that you think
was the best match for your
scenario and you also have the option to
uh go back to the input prompt by
clicking the title of the page here that
will take you back to the the input mode
basically also here at the bottom of the
output uh page you have the option to
regenerate the AI output simply just
retry and see what does it come up with
if if you run it again you could of
course also discard the output if you
just want to you know go back to scratch
so even before you start the feature
this will close the prompt dialogue and
of course you can accept you can um
accept it if you find it use
useful and here you have the option to
decide what kind of options should be
there for um uh applying different
variations of of input so that you get a
different output in this case of the
marketing text feature you have tone and
format and
emphasis so with that let's just go and
see another demo where we start with
structured data and end also with
structured data so here I'm on a
purchase order and I have an opportunity
now to use copilot to map the lines from
the e doent that was matched to this
purchase order with the lines from this
purchase order so I hit the map eent
action and what we see here is that we
actually skip the input mode because we
had all the input we needed no need to
directag the user through an input stage
so we could go directly to the
generating mode and then after that
directly to the output mode and you see
here that based on the inputs we were
able to create some structured outputs
in this case we matched uh purchase
order lines using co-pilot so this was
just an example of we came from some
structured input no need to involve the
user in the input stage we skip that
part go directly to generating and then
to the output so it's a it's a good
thing for you to consider your scenario
do I have structured data or not do I
need to involve the user is there
anything that they can decide in that
input process in terms of
um things that will impact the output
here it's much structured no need to
involve the user after seeing these
demos yakob can you take us through um
the more general concepts with air
experiences in in businesses and and uh
and make us wiser on that thanks s great
demos and as you uh mentioned we will
take now a a more high level view on the
AI experiences and how to design for
them and if you want to die into the
demos that s showed in more detail there
are other sessions in the launch event
here that you can uh click into but let
let's zoom out a moment uh and talk
about AI experiences because as as
compelling these scenarios are it is a
novel um type of experience and we have
found in our research that it takes a
little getting used to uh both for uh
people uh working with this and
designing for it so uh having what we
call new mental models for AI is
important and part of that is
understanding what can AI do what is it
good for and what uh uh is still sort of
primarily uh the humans uh problem
solving skills
required and what we have found when we
have interviewed uh business users is
that of course there are experts in
their domain of of business uh and they
are very knowledgeable about what they
do and and why um but most business
users are not AI experts it's not
necessarily clear what AI um is best for
at this point in time and lastly
building trust using AI uh requires that
the users are comfortable with uh the
limitations of AI and and really um
diving into uh the AI advantages require
that that uh trust to be in place so how
can we support that trust and and that's
something that we have spent a good deal
of time on understanding how can AI be
integrated so that it supports business
users in a great
way so I'm listing here some of the uh
many tasks that AI can uh support users
in and again following the news and the
hype around AI um these are just at at
lmse of what people have uh proposed as
great ways to support users with AI
simplify solving task get quicker
insights understand relationships and so
on so a very broad pallette of ways that
AI can uh help the business users but we
can also bucket these uh in a way and
see well uh at the end of the day maybe
this is about two things primarily AI
can help taking action to do something
more F faster or more efficient and a I
can help gain insights uh get to
knowledge around the the domain of
business in ways that haven't been a
possible before as
easily so let's look at the action part
here the user expresses a desire has an
attention you saw CERN instead of
manually filling in the sales line he
just typed what items he wanted and AI
was quickly able to pull those lines and
create them into the uh uh to the sales
orderer of course with one line uh the
gain is maybe not so great but you can
easily imagine uh scenarios where you
want to fill in 20 or 25 lines anything
that can speed up that process is is
going to help
greatly next up um getting Insight
knowing when to do what uh knowing uh uh
what you you need to know to be
proactive in your business is also a
great uh potential of AI now and and
especially going
forward so how does AI know what to
suggest what to take action about and
again a a glimpse into some of the data
context that is available for an AI
engine such as
co-pilot uh are uh mentioned here so in
business Central uh business Central
knows what page is on the screen at a
given point in time so it knows what the
user is looking at in business Central
uh it knows what the user have been
doing in business Central in terms terms
of what orders has been touched created
and so on co-pilot also has access to
data uh and and it knows what the user
is is job roles are typically and it
knows how data is changing so what is
trending so all these data sources are
potentially input to co-pilot in terms
of suggesting and helping the user uh be
productive now we also need to talk
about the situation where things can go
wrong because there are as you've also
I'm sure heard about is that AI is not
necessarily making the right uh um
guesses or predictions all the time so
you can get uh ungrounded information
from Ai and this is just a fact of how
AI works now and probably also going
forward so the wisdom here is that
instead of trying to rule out all um
wrongdoings of AI we need to bracket it
we need to control Ro we need to
understand and put up safeguards because
AI will always be uh failing from time
to time so the the the research here
that I'm U quoting is that um no AI will
be ever perfect because no model can
interact with the physical world in a
complete way so human needs to be in the
loop as it Set uh to uh control and
understand what AI is doing uh so we we
can get the benefits without uh the risk
so how do we do that well how to manage
generative AI
risks so there again back to uh the
previous point there are two ways we
need to manage risk there is what we can
call detrimental actions um AI may
suggest actions which are undesirable so
taking a very simple example it could
have picked the wrong item when C asked
for um
a certain item it could have found
another item for him so that is
obviously uh undesirable but with very
little side effects however we need to
deal with these situations there's also
what we under one called the ungrounded
reasoning meaning that the AI is
suggesting an Insight that happens to be
uh Incorrect and it can be incorrect for
a number of different ways that we won't
go into here but we will talk more about
how how we deal with these situations in
terms of actions the main point around
uh dealing with action is that we need
to provide users a way to either undo or
preview what the AI is suggesting of an
action so now we are talking about what
we call the responsible AI principles
and a very important principle is that
the system in this case business Central
must always provide a preview or a way
to completely undo what AI
suggested the second Mantra is that when
a business Central is showing some
generated information or
inside we will always Mark that
information and when possible attach a
confidence level to the information so
the user is informed that this piece of
information is generated by Ai and
secondly in situation where it's
possible provide a confidence level for
that piece of information so let's look
at uh how this turns plays out in
practice so you just saw cern's example
with a sales order and what he did here
was he had a s situation that was a
document and he asked for some lines to
be added and AI generated those lines
and came with a preview of the suggested
lines in what we call the prompt
dialogue then that that we will talk
more about in a minute the user can in
this particular case choose to keep it
and when the user keeps it those lines
are added to the uh sales order so if
the user had pressed the discard button
then those lines would be discarded and
the user would be back at the sales
order without any lines added so in
summary responsible AI means provider
preview or undo uh and when the user
decides to undo discard what the user
generated so a lot of the interaction
and experience around business Central
revolves around the prompt dialogue so
in this next section we will talk a bit
about the prompt dialogue and how to
design it and the features it has at the
moment let me add that um in terms of
co-pilot experiences I'm sure a lot of
you might uh be looking for information
about how to extend chat the co-pilot
chat in business Central that is not
part of this session and currently there
is no uh partner extensibility for the
chat in uh business Central what is uh
the main vehicle for AI experiences in
business Central at the moment is the
promt dialogue so uh that is exactly
what we will go through next so as son
mentioned and in the demo around the
eents and the matching of sales lines um
s mentioned that the prompt input I mean
the instruction to the generation step
is actually optional and that means that
very often the context for what AI is
going to generate is already present in
business Central in the case with
matching lines those lines have already
been added on the E document and on the
purchase uh uh orders so it's all a
matter of matching up the lines and
since that should happen according to a
fairly well- defined set of rules
there's no need to let the user provide
any prompt input for that particular
operation we can just go straight to the
generation step
so the next step the generation steps is
certainly a required step the generate
step is where the large language model
is contacted and it is coming back with
some uh uh data that is then bound into
business Central in a in a way that
matching the scenario and the content
output is shown to the user so in the
content output stage that is where the
user will review what has been generated
and they will decide to either keep or
discard that particular
input if the user presses keep it of
course we are moving data from the
temporary table usually where it's
stored to the actual table where that
data um uh will be
persisted so how does that look in at
the AL level layer um this is not a
developer or engineering session but we
will just touch briefly on the AL
structures because it's useful to know
at the conceptual basis is what is a
promt dialogue actually uh uh containing
um and the promt dialogue is going to be
with us from now and going forward and
and it will complement the other page
types we have in business Central such
as standard dialogue confirmation
dialogue cards and Page documents and so
on so this is a new page type that has
been developed for business Central
exactly to uh encapsulate and and hold
these experiences related to
AI so the page type as it says here is
prom diog prom dialog and what it has is
a few sets of new areas so those of you
who are uh knowing a will notice that
the prompt area and the prompt options
area are also new areas in a page the
content area has been there uh all the
time uh and it's also used with other
page
types so this is where concretely to s
uh explanation the input is uh
uh defined in the prompt part so it can
be free text to the for the unstructured
input it can be a um list or it can be
an a control of some sort if if it's
related to a structured
input The Prompt option section is where
you are putting fields that are you
could say parameters to The Prompt so
you could choose how for example the
tone of voice uh or the length or some
common ways of adjusting the output can
go there as prompt options these will
have to be option Fields so no no other
data types than option fields are
allowed in the prompt
options let me say here that that the
user um can use prompt options but it's
a good practice never to require the
user to choose the prompt options what
can be required is the prompt but the
prompt options should never be required
and and we have found in our research
that actually sometimes users don't even
notice that there are options so it's a
good practice not to assume that the
user is going to tweak the options uh in
a given case simply user could default
so so it it doesn't matter too much if
the user don't knows it it they can just
go back and and maybe Discover it
later next up in the prompt dialogue is
the are the the system actions so most
importantly the generate system action
is the code that will be run when the
user hits generate in the prom
dialogue and maybe needless to say um
the system action okay and and cancel
will be called when the user either
decides to uh discard or keep the output
so for the AL developer they are
responsible for providing the AL code
that make uh these system actions
actually provide the experience that the
user is
expecting and what are they expecting
well it may be redundant but let me just
state it again it's very very important
that when you are developing a new prom
dialogue that you obey to this principle
of uh undoing
uh so that the user can safely generate
something in AI regret and hit discard
and then all traces of that needs to go
away so it's a good practice not to put
any data from the generated output
anywhere but in the temporary table
supporting the prompt dialogue because
that's really the only way that you can
secure that the user can discard and
things are gone so don't make any side
effects of the generated output because
that way you are uh not allowing the
user to roll
back continuing on the promp dialogue um
the next uh thing you saw also in s's
example was that there is a small
instructional text that the user can
that helps the user understand what kind
of prompt is expected in this situation
so in this particular case it was
describe the lines you'd like to create
and co-pilot will get you started that
is what we call sometimes it's called
the the ghost text or the placeholder
text text whatever you call it uh its
purpose is to give an instruction to the
user about what they should type
here next feature of the prompt dialogue
is known as The Prompt guide there was
an example in in a sence demo right away
but you have probably seen the
principles in in other Microsoft pro
programs uh the icon here sometimes Al
called called the Spellbook will allow
the user to get access to some
suggestions for what they can use of
prompt so they simply pick from a menu
maybe you group The prompts like these
are related to copying these are related
to um uh adding and so on and then for
each group there will be relevant prompt
um uh so the user can get a jump start
on their own uh prompting and we have
done that because prompting is not going
to feel natural to every user so this is
an important way of giving them some
templates to work from when they
formulate their own
prompts all
right now let's say you've built the
promp dialoges and now you want to allow
the user to trigger those prompt
dialogues from your application so what
I'll explain here are the few of the
options that are now available to place
prompt actions uh that will trigger
prompt dialogues into the business
Central
UI so most prominently um we have
actually placed it front and center of
all list places so there is now a thing
called the co-pilot menu that is
available to prompt actions on every
list it is even possible now to have a
uh the cold P pilot menu be a uh element
that is sort of overlaid on the page for
maximum
discoverability so this will let you
put uh prompt actions in a very
prominent place so that users can easily
get started on invoking uh your great
co-pilot
actions when the menu is called up it
will show all the co-pilot actions
defined in that page and you will also
notice that some of those prompt actions
are defined by the app others are
defined by the system so also explained
in another uh launch session here are
the analysis assists analysis assist is
a prompt action that is defined by the
system and also available on all list
Pages the menu inside the page has the
same choices as the action bar plus one
as you can see here the lower one is
called hide for those users who don't
feel they want a floating
co-pilot menu they can decide to hide
that and then it is only available in
the action
bar the floating co-pilot menu is clever
because it allows oneclick access to the
most the topmost action of those in the
page here so you can see how in this
particular case reconcile gets a very
very prominent positioning for uh that
page and the use user is likely to uh
discover that as the one of the first
things when they get into the list so
use that space wisely for an action that
actually is supposed to be very
prominent um so uh we are making good
use of of that
prominence next up uh in terms of prompt
actions are the dialogue the standard
dialogue also has a capability of
providing a prompt action so that's a
very a a brilliant way of having a
co-pilot actions appearing in the
context of a dialogue and you've
probably seen in relation to the uh
marketing text feature that that
particular action is available when you
are writing a marketing
text we are getting to the uh few last
slides around prom dialoges and actions
um we don't have any co-pilot menu on
the entity page yet so cards and
documents don't have that capability
that lists have yet um but the sub Pages
have so you can put a co-pilot action
into a sub page and that is exactly what
we were using uh in the demo s showed
where the suggest sales lines uh has
been put and um in situations where you
want the user to be able to discover the
prompt actions you can either use the
menu uh as uh with a with a co-pilot
icon or you can use the existing action
bar and place your actions there uh and
we recommend this so-called Sparkle
action to represent those actions that
trigger some kind of
AI all right over to you son about the
prom dialogue thank you so much yob um
this was really great insight about how
to how to structure and how to use the
prompt dialogue so call to action for
you is now to get familiar with the
prompt dialogue um spin up a trial of of
business Central and and start playing
around with it um also uh try out these
features in in Al and and and and and
and start building your your first AI
features um but importantly as you've
now seen throughout this session is
consider the best use of the prompt
dialogue for every scenario meaning what
type of input do you have what kind of
output do you expect to produce with it
structured versus unstructured or in
between so um one way to get started is
to uh to grab a demo environment from
what we call CDX which is the partner uh
demo space where you can sign in with
your partner account and and get a
tenant um we suggest that you add a new
profile in in in Microsoft Edge that
allows you to to store the credentials
for this demo environment so you have
easy access to that and then sign up for
a business Cal business Central trial um
on that on that
environment um if you can find co-pilot
uh here are some things that you can
check so first of all you can check the
co-pilot and AI capabilities page you
could simply just search for that in the
tell me
search um and um check that and make
sure that the features are active here
and there are some other things you see
here that that that you can check uh for
example right now we only support
English language so make sure that
English is selected as your language and
also this is from what we call version
24 uh meaning 2024 wave
1 there are some other great launch
event sessions that you should check out
that goes into more details with some of
the demos we've just seen so for example
these two demos with uh creating sales
line suggestions with co-pilot and E
invoice matching with co-pilot check
those sessions out they go into much
more details about how these features
work and to which extent you can use
them also um what yakob mentioned
there's the AI powered analysis with
co-pilot that's a great session as well
well we will show you how to use the
analysis mode and generate analysis tabs
with with co-pilot by describing what
you want to see and there's of course a
more technical session that is extending
co-pilot using a code that we'll go into
more details with what yakob just showed
in terms of how to how to structure your
Al code and and um and make it uh Best
in Class for creating Copa
features there's also a lot of great
content out there already so uh take a
screenshot of this uh of this screen
here I won't go through all of them but
here you can get access to all the
information both Technical and
non-technical so that you can have
discussions in your teams about what
kind of co-pilot features do we want to
build for our
customers and to on top of that on the
more General
resources for business Central here's
also a lot of great stuff for you uh if
I should point to just one of these is
the bottom one that says aka. msbz all
that basically links to all the rest so
if you you know Rec you know internalize
Just One Source from this it's it's it's
that
one so with that we would like to thank
you for watching this business Central
launch event session and hope to see you
again